<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the aldermen, and governours of the several hospitals of the city of London, at St. Bridget's Church on Easter-Monday, 1700 by ... William, Lord Bishop of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12068997</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12068997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 582:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the aldermen, and governours of the several hospitals of the city of London, at St. Bridget's Church on Easter-Monday, 1700 by ... William, Lord Bishop of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Warren, for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 30.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XV, 22-24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53466:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53466:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Right Honourable THE Lord Mayor, THE ALDERMEN, AND Governours of the ſeveral Hoſpitals of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At St. <hi>Bridget</hi>'s Church On <hi>Eaſter-Monday,</hi> 1700.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Warren,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> at the Half-Moon in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53466:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53466:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN xv. 22.</hi>
                  </bibl> If I had not come, and ſpoken unto them, they had not had Sin; but now have they no Cloke for their Sin.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN xv. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that hateth me, hateth my Father alſo.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN xv. 24.</hi>
                  </bibl> If I had not done among them the Works which none other Man did, they had not had Sin; but now have they both ſeen, and hated both me, and my Father.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Churches Obſervation of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at this time calls for a Diſcourſe upon our Lord's Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Reſpect to the particular Occaſion of the meeting of this Honourable Aſſembly, would direct me to the ſubject of Charity.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry to add, that the bold and daring attempts, that are at this Day made upon our Religion in general, neceſſarily require ſomething to be ſaid upon ſo Publick an Occaſion, in Vindication of it.</p>
            <p>I hope I may in ſome meaſure Anſwer all theſe Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by attempting to prove the truth of our Religion; as from other Miracles wrought for the Confirmation of it, ſo chiefly from our Saviour's Reſurrection; by which he was <hi>declared to be the Son of God with Power,</hi> and by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring in my Application to perſwade you to Evidence to your ſelves and the World the ſincerity of your Faith in this Religion, by a Practice conformable to the Holy Laws of it, and particularly to that, which in the Extent where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is injoin'd us by our Religion is peculiar to it; that of Charity: There is ſo cloſe a Connection, betwixt the Chriſtian Religion and Charity, that he, that aſſerts the Chriſtian Religion, is one of the beſt Advocates for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and he that truly practiſes Charity, one of the beſt Pleaders for the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53466:3"/>
            <p>In the Verſes of my Text, and thoſe immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, our Lord is arming his Apoſtles againſt two great diſcouragements they were like to meet with in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Office, <hi>viz.</hi> A violent Perſecution of their Perſons, and a mighty Oppoſition to their Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Of both theſe he tells them, he had had his ſhare, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Relation they ſtood in to him, that they were his Servants, and he their Lord, they could not think it ſtrange if they ſhould not be better treated than he had been: Theſe things therefore they ought to expect and prepare for, and for their ſupport under them he adds, <hi>All theſe things will they do unto you for my Names ſake,</hi> all the Perſecutions, Reproaches and Deſpiteful uſage, that ſhall befall you, will be upon my ſcore, who ſurely have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from you, and am able abundantly to make up to you, whatever you can ſuffer upon my account: And for the Oppoſition which Wicked Men will make to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines you are to Preach, let not that affright you, for I having ſo plainly propoſed it to the World, as a Doctrine that came from God, and ſo evidently demonſtrated it to be ſo, that they cannot Plead ignorance or want of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction; their Infidelity who ſhall oppoſe it, will be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, and their rejecting of it, interpreted by God, to be a Malicious reſiſting and Contemning of me, and him too. <hi>If I had not come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What our Lord ſuppoſed would be the condition of his Religion, and the Preachers of it then, is too plainly the caſe of both at this time.</p>
            <p>'Tis pretty hard that after near 1700 Years Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Title of the Chriſtian Religion to Truth ſhould be call'd into Queſtion: But ſo it is, Arguments are urged for Natural Religion, in Oppoſition to any Reveal'd one, the riſe and progreſs of the Chriſtian in particular, is aſcribed to Policy and Deſign in ſome, and to Credulity, and a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to hearken to any Impoſtor in others: the Holy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it is treated with thoſe Inſolencies and Blaſphemies,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53466:3"/>which it could not but be as uneaſie to you to hear, as to me to repeat them: To give only one inſtance, his riding into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is impiouſly repreſented under the light Expreſſion of <hi>making his Cavalcade upon his Aſinego.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orac. of Reaſ. <hi>P.</hi> 165.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe horrible Blaſphemies, have been not only once impudently Printed and Publiſh'd to the World, under the Pompous Titles of <hi>Oracles of Reaſon</hi> in the Life time of the Author; but ſince the death of that unhappy Man, Reprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with other of his Wretched Works, and an Epiſtle before them, placing the Author in Heaven, and giving his Works the Characters of <hi>ſacred Monuments; Truths of too great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to be ſlightly run-over, of too great Beauty not to hold our Eyes ſometime on them.</hi> And theſe by the way are ſome of the Excellent fruits of that <hi>Liberty of the Preſs,</hi> for which that Author was ſo Zealous an Advocate.
<note place="margin">Juſt Vindication of Learning, and the Liberty of the Preſs.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After this Treatment of our Lord, no uſage of us his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters can be ſurpriſing, <hi>if they have called the Maſter of the Houſe Belzebub,</hi> what muſt <hi>they of the Houſhold</hi> expect? We cannot wonder at their charging us with Hypocriſie and Deceit, Self-Intereſt, and Worldly Deſigns, and what not.</p>
            <p>Nay ſo far as all theſe reproaches affect us only, we can, I hope, not only patiently endure, but even <hi>rejoice that we are counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for the Name of Chriſt, to bear his reproach, and to fill up what is behind of his Sufferings:</hi> And in Obedience to his Command, and Conformity to his example, forgive and pray for thoſe that thus Deſpitefully uſe us, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi> I wiſh we could add, <hi>They know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſo far as theſe contumelies affect our Maſter and his Religion, and they are wounded through us, as moſt certainly an affront offer'd to an Ambaſſador as ſuch, does not reſt in him, but reaches the Prince that gave him his Character, and as certainly they that are endeavouring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53466:4"/>to bring a contempt upon the Prieſt's Office, and render it uſeleſs, are aiming at our Religion; for if they can deſtroy the Prieſthood (as ſome ſpeak their intentions pretty plainly) the Diſcipline and Ordinances of Chriſt cannot be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and if our Publick Ordinances were once laid aſide, 'twould not be poſſible long to keep up a Face of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; upon theſe views we may be allow'd to be Jealous of the Honour of our Maſter and his Inſtitutions, and ſhall not ſurely be thought to carry our Reſentments too far, by making that return to their Inſolencies and Blaſphemies, which the <hi>Archangel</hi> made to one of old, famous for his <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, the Lord Rebuke them,</hi> and by oppoſing to their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent attempts to render our Religion ſuſpected, thoſe ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rafragable Arguments for the Truth of it, which muſt prevail wherever Reaſon is permitted to be judge.</p>
            <p>So far am I from affronting <hi>Reaſon,
<note place="margin">Preface to Orac. Reaſ.</note> that Sovereign Guide,</hi> as 'tis call'd, or from <hi>infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its liberty of directing,</hi> even in the choice of a Religion, that I do very freely acknowledge, that a Religion, which cannot be Reaſonably accounted for, is not fit for a Rational Creature to own, nor worth his keeping.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak of a Religion in groſs; a Man ought to know upon what grounds he takes it up before he profeſſes one, and to be able to give better Reaſons for it, than becauſe it is the Religion of the Country wherein he lives, or that wherein he was educated.</p>
            <p>He that embraces a Religion without any, or any good Reaſon, is likely enough to part with it upon as eaſie Terms.</p>
            <p>He that owns one meerly becauſe it is profeſt in the Country wherein he lives, muſt change one as often as he does the other.</p>
            <p>He that Pleads Education, urges an Argument common to all Religions, and ſince all cannot be true, an Argument, that may be equally uſed for all muſt needs be Bad.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53466:4"/>
            <p>A Man ſhould therefore well examine the force of thoſe Motives that are offer'd to him, to perſwade him to be of this or that Religion, and not give himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to any, but that which is proved to be the true one, by ſuch Arguments, as agree to that and to no other, and ſuch as will be of weight with him in all times and places, and ſufficient to prevail with a prudent and conſidering Man, to adventure ſo great a ſtake thereupon, as the Everlaſting condition of his Immortal Soul, and ſuch Arguments for the Chriſtian Religion has our Saviour furniſhed us with, in the Words of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If, ſays he, I had not come and ſpoke unto them,</hi> (i. e.) If I had not come according to the Ancient Predictions, and appear'd publickly in the World as a Prophet ſent by God, and Preach'd a Doctrine as from him, ſo Pure and Holy, that it plainly carry'd his Image and Superſcription upon it, <hi>They had not had Sin,</hi> (i. e.) they might have had the Plea of Ignorance, but, <hi>now they have no Cloke for their Sin,</hi> i. e. no pretence, no colour of an excuſe to cover their incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I had not done among them the Works which none other Man did,</hi> i. e. if I had not juſtifyed my Miſſion, Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Doctrine to be from God, by Working ſuch Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles for the proof of them, which no Man could do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Divine aſſiſtance, their rejecting of me, and my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine might have been more Pardonable, <hi>But now they have both ſeen and hated both me and my Father's,</hi> (i. e.) they have ſeen him, his Power in thoſe Works which I have wrought in his Name, and their rejecting my Doctrine for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation whereof he ſo plainly appear'd, is a Malicious oppoſing not of me only, but of the Father himſelf.</p>
            <p>So that from hence I might take occaſion to inſiſt upon two Arguments for the proof of the Chriſtian Religion; one taken from thoſe internal Marks of Divinity which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in it, the Holineſs and Purity of what our Saviour ſpake or taught, the other from thoſe External evidences
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53466:5"/>which we have of its Truth in the Miraculous Works, which were wrought for the atteſtation of it.</p>
            <p>But the firſt of theſe, though it be an excellent and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Argument for our Religion, with unbyaſſed, Pious, and well diſpoſed Minds, yet it will hardly have its due weight with ſuch Adverſaries as we have to deal with, nay, in truth, it is rather, I fear, the true ground of their oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, for to apply, what one of their great Maſters has ſaid of Reaſon to Religion, if Religion <hi>be againſt a Man, a Man will be againſt</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore at this time confine my ſelf to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Argument, which is taken from thoſe Works, which were wrought for the proof of our Religion, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly that ſignal one, the raiſing of the Holy Author of it from the Dead.</p>
            <p>In order to the more regular proceeding; I muſt ſtate the Queſtion with the Deiſt, and lay down ſome demands ſo reaſonable, that he ſhall be aſhamed to deny them.</p>
            <p>The diſpute is not between Natural and Reveal'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for both one and the other are from God, who cannot differ from himſelf, but the queſtion is between us, and the Deiſts, as they call themſelves, whether God has left Men as to the way of Worſhiping and Serving him, to the light of Nature only, to thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe common Notices of Good and Evil, which are naturally implanted in their Hearts, or whether he has made any farther diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his Will by the Miniſtry of any that he has ſent into the World for that end, and particularly by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I aſſert the latter part of the Queſtion, and to make way for my Argument, lay down.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That God can, if he Pleaſes, make known or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Religion to Men by an External Revelation.</p>
            <p>Natural Religion and Reveal'd Religion are not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly oppoſed, but that Natural Religion is a Reveal'd Religion, but it is Reveal'd by an Internal way of Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53466:5"/>whereas that which we eſpecially mean by Reveal'd Religion is diſcover'd by an External way of Propoſal: Now they that contend that God has diſcovered a Religion by an Internal way of Propoſal, cannot deny but that he may, if he will, diſcover one by an External way, by raiſing up and impowering fit inſtruments for that Purpoſe; one of theſe does no more imply a Contradiction than the other, nor is more repugnant to any of the Divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and God can do whatever implies not a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That, if it appear that ſuch Teſtimony has been given to an External Revelation, as none but God could give, ſuch Works wrought and appeal'd to for the proof of the Truth and Divinity thereof, which could not be effected without a Divine Aſſiſtance; This is an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evidence that God has made ſuch a Revelation: For if God has put forth his Power to atteſt that a Revelation came from him, either what is ſo atteſted is true, or God, who is eſſential Truth, has given his Teſtimony and Seal to a lie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That thoſe who have the cleareſt and beſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that ſuch Divine Teſtimony has been given to the Truth, and Divinity of an External Revelation, that a thing of that Nature is capable of, and ſuch as ſuppoſing it true, they could not have had better, have all the reaſon that can be to ſubmit to it, and if they do not, <hi>have no Cloke for their Sin,</hi> no Plea for their Infidelity, for they reſiſt the utmoſt Conviction that can be had.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I will go on in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I will ſhew that thoſe Works which we ſay were wrought for the proof of the Chriſtian Religion, eſpecially the reſurrection of Chriſt from the Dead, were ſuch as could not have been effected by any Power leſs than Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:53466:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. I will prove that we have the beſt evidence, that ſuch Works were wrought for that purpoſe, that the matter is capable of, and ſuch as we could not have had better, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it true.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will enquire what Cloke the Unbeliever has for his Sin, what Plea he can offer, what excuſe he can pretend for his infidelity. And,</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall conclude with ſome practical Application with regard to the particular occaſion of our meeting</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Works, which we ſay were wrought for the proof of the Chriſtian Religion, were ſuch as no Perſon, unaſſiſted with a Divine Power, could have done: They were, commanding the Winds and Seas, ſtilling Tempeſts, caſting out Devils, cleanſing Lepers, healing the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate Diſeaſes, reſtoring the Deaf to their Hearing, and giving Sight and uſe of Limbs, to thoſe who were born Blind and Lame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all theſe were done in ſo many Moments, without the Application of any, or any competent means for the effecting of them, by a bare Touch, or but Speaking a Word, and yet the effects were real and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Blind, Deaf, and Lame, immediately Seeing, Hearing, Walking, and continuing ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Now by what Power, leſs than Divine, could theſe things have been done?</p>
            <p>As for Nature, if theſe things are within the compaſs of her Working, not beyond the Laws preſcribed her, but ſuch as might be done by ſome ſecret and unknown Power in her, 'Tis very ſtrange that ſhe never exerted that Power before nor ſince: But I ſhall only ask how the Author, and firſt Planters of the Chriſtian Religion, came to be upon the ſecret, at that time privy to that deſign of hers, of putting herſelf forth in ſuch an extraordinary manner then, that they could exactly know the minute when, the object about which, and the inſtance wherein ſhe would exerciſe that Power, which till that time had lain Dormant in her, and that ſo certainly, that they could confidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53466:6"/>thereto for the Truth of what they taught, and let the Credit of their Doctrine depend thereupon? Men that have Curiouſly enquired into Nature, may from Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations which they have made upon their own or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Experience, that ſuch and ſuch things have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened upon ſuch and ſuch Conjunctures, when they ſee the like Conjunctures, foretell, that probably the ſame effects will follow: But if Men ſhall certainly foreknow that ſtrange things beyond the Ordinary courſe of Nature will happen at ſuch a time, which never happened before, and of which therefore they could have no Experience to ground an Obſervation upon; if the Work it ſelf were not above Nature, yet the foreknowledge of it muſt be Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and from God alone. And the Revealing of things of this kind to a Perſon, whereby he is enabled to appeal to them for the truth of what he Teaches, will as effectually bring in God for a Voucher of his Doctrine, as if the Works themſelves had been done by his immediate Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But whatever may be pretended of others, ſome at leaſt of thoſe Works, which we ſay were wrought by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor for the Proof of our Religion, are ſuch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly beyond the Power of Nature, or any Created Being.</p>
            <p>And thoſe are, his raiſing of ſeveral, and Himſelf at the laſt, from the Dead: Thoſe that deny all Miracles, own that theſe would be Miracles, if they ever were or ſhould be done.</p>
            <p>Theſe things then being granted to be beyond the reach of any Power leſs than Infinite, the Evidence of Fact that they have been done, and that for the atteſtation of the truth of the Chriſtian Religion, ſhall be made out in my next.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Propoſition, and that by the beſt proof a thing of this Nature is capable of: I ſay, the beſt proof it is capable of, for all things are not capable of Mathematical, or Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſical Evidence: Matters of Fact which happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our time or in diſtant places from us, are capable of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53466:7"/>no other than that which we call Moral proof; but if they are proved by the beſt Evidence of that ſort, they are as well proved in their kind, as Propoſitions in either of thoſe Sciences which are Demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Moral Evidence, that the above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts were done for the proof of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, we have them recorded in a Venerable Hiſtory, againſt which none of thoſe Objections can be Juſtly made, which can render the Authority of any Hiſtory ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>For if there be reaſon to ſuſpect the truth of any Hiſtory, it muſt be upon the account of either the Book or the Author.</p>
            <p>If upon the account of the Book, it is either becauſe the Book is in the whole Spurious, not written by the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author, but the Work of ſome later Impoſtor; or elſe becauſe it is faulty in part, having been Interpolated or Corrupted.</p>
            <p>If upon the account of the Author, it muſt be becauſe he had not either ſufficient Opportunity of knowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the matters he relates, or honeſty enough to relate truly what he did know: Either he was impoſed upon, believing thoſe things to fall out which did not, or elſe he had a deſign to impoſe upon others.</p>
            <p>But where none of theſe things can be reaſonably ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, where we have good grounds to believe a Book to be genuine, intire and pure, and the Author both knowing and honeſt, well acquainted himſelf with what he relates, and without any deſign to lead others into Error; in ſuch a caſe there can be no cauſe, nor pretence of a cauſe, to doubt of the truth of a Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Now that the Books wherein theſe Miracles are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Books of the New Teſtament are genuine, we have certain information from the very Men,
<note place="margin">Clem. Roman. Ignat. Polycarp.</note> that knew and converſed with the Writers of them. Thoſe that lived in the time of the Authors, and converſed with them, had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53466:7"/>opportunities of knowing whether the Books were genuine or not, and it mightily concern'd them to enquire nicely, and be well ſatisfyed that they were ſo; and no doubt they were upon inquiry ſo ſatisfyed, when they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the truth of them, with the utmoſt hazard of what was deareſt to them in this World, and ventured likewiſe thereupon their Eternal Salvation in the next: We find theſe Books tranſmitted as Authentick to the next Generation, and receiv'd as ſuch by them,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>Juſtin M. Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>us, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologists.</p>
                  <p>Tertull.</p>
               </note> nay, the very Originals appeal'd to, as remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the end of the Second Age.</p>
            <p>Of the truth of theſe Books they were ſo unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſatisfyed in the next, that rather than deliver up theſe Books to their Perſecutors, they choſe to give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſevereſt Torments and Deaths.</p>
            <p>And from thence we have an uninterrupted Tradition of the truth, and genuineſs of them continued down to our times.</p>
            <p>And as they are genuine, ſo that they are pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted, the early diſperſing them into diſtant places, and tranſlating them into ſeveral Languages, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any one to doubt: For ſince in all the Copies and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations now Extant, there is ſuch a perfect agreement in the main, that they hardly differ in any thing of great Moment, how can it be imagined, that ſo many Men of different Countries and Tongues, living remotely, and having little Commerce with each other, ſhould all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire together to falſify their Copies, to put ſuch a cheat upon themſelves and their Poſterity, as to interpolate thoſe Books, which they believed and aſſerted to be Divine, and contain the <hi>Words of Eternal Life,</hi> and tranſmit them ſo corrupted to Ages to come?</p>
            <p>For the Writers of theſe Books, that they could not but know, whether the matters which they related were true or falſe, is certain from the Facts themſelves, which being Matters of Sence, they were very Competent Judges of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53466:8"/>them, and which they do not relate as done in Ages paſt and places remote, which they do not take upon truſt, nor tell upon hearſay, but as done in their own time and fight.</p>
            <p>If therefore they have related that which is falſe, they muſt have done it knowing and deſignedly.</p>
            <p>But that they ſhould feign what they wrote, deſigning to abuſe the World, cannot be ſuſpected by any that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they were honeſt and harmleſs Men, of unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Converſations, that they were mean illiterate Perſons, hardly capable of inventing to coherent a Story: That there was no advantage they could propoſe to themſelves from it, but contrarywiſe they expoſed themſelves by it to ignominy and contempt, to Poverty and ſpoiling of their Goods, to Impriſonment, Tortures and Death.</p>
            <p>But let it be ſuppoſed, that they had Wickedneſs and Malice enough to deſign to abuſe the World, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to ſerve by ſo doing, and withal Wit and Skill enough to contrive ſuch a plauſible Fable; yet how could they ever hope to make it paſs upon the World, when they wrote in the very place that was the Scene of all thoſe ſtrange Works which they reported, and addreſs'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the very Men before whom they were done, and that whilſt they were freſh in their Memories, appealing to them for the truth of them?</p>
            <p>Certainly if theſe things were Fictions, to go about to impoſe them in ſuch a manner upon Men, muſt argue thoſe that attempted it to be plainly Diſtracted and out of their Wits, either they had too little Sence to invent theſe Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or too much to hope to make them believe them to whom they related them: For Men cannot be deceived in Matters concerning which appeal is made to their Sences: Strange Stories of things pretended to be done in times of Old, or Foreign Countries, may though falſe, when confidently reported, paſs upon eaſie People, but no Credulity can be ſo great as to be perſuaded by any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53466:8"/>Confidence, or Impudence rather, that Matters of Face which were not done at all, were done in ones Preſence and Sight.</p>
            <p>If then what theſe Men relate were falſe, ſince thoſe to whom they directed their reports could not but know they were ſo as well as themſelves, ſure no folly ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual'd that of the Relators, except haply that of thoſe that could believe them: And yet we find many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands believing theſe Relations, reverencing the Authors of them, embracing the Religion they Preached, and for the proof of which thoſe Miracles were done and related; and for the ſake thereof, forſaking the Gods they had Worſhipped, renouncing the Religion they had been Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in, ſacrificing their Luſts and Vices, and not count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Lives dear to them: So that either there were ſuch Miracles wrought as theſe Perſons related, or this at leaſt muſt be one, that thoſe relations ſhould obtain ſo much Credit in the World.</p>
            <p>Having thus aſſerted the Authority of the Hiſtory, I beg leave to conſider a little more particularly ſome of the Facts recorded in it.</p>
            <p>In this Book then we meet with a long train of Miracles, Works beyond the Power of Nature or any Created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wrought by a Perſon, that profeſſes himſelf ſent by God to Reveal his Mind and Will to the World, to which Miracles he conſtantly appeals for the Proof of his Miſſion and Doctrine. <hi>Believe me for the Works ſake, I have grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teſtimony than that of John, the Works that I do in my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name bear Witneſs of me, and if I by the Finger of God caſt out Devils, no doubt the Kingdom of God is come unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in a more eſpecial manner his Reſurrection is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted as the moſt Demonſtrative proof of his being ſent by God.</p>
            <p>To raiſe the Dead is an uncontroverted Prerogative of the Deity, and certainly and diſtinctly to foretel future
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53466:9"/>Contingencies is ſo too: Now in the Goſpel we read that when the Jews came to Chriſt, twice deſiring a ſign of him, that he would ſhew his Credentials, make ſome proof of his Commiſſion and Authority, he tells them once, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple,</hi> (ſpeaking of the Temple of his Body) <hi>and in three Days I will raiſe it up.</hi> And another time, <hi>no other ſign ſhall be given but the ſign of the Prophet</hi> Jonas. <hi>For as</hi> Jonas <hi>was three Days and Nights in the Belly of the Whale, ſo the San of Man ſhall be three Days and Nights in the Heart of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here he lays the Credit and Authority of all that he aſſerted concerning himſelf, or taught them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the falling out of a thing future, and that a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to Nature or any Created Being; upon his riſing from the Dead the third Day after they ſhould Kill him: And as he foretold, it fell out, after they that had Crucifyed him, were ſatisfyed that he was Dead, had lay'd him in a New Tomb, and to prevent any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to ſteal away his Body, had Seal'd the Sepulchre, and ſet a ſtrong Watch to guard it; the third Day the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre was found empty, the Linen Cloths that his Body was wrapt in lying there, but his Body was gone.</p>
            <p>Their pretence that after all the precaution they had uſed, his Diſciples came by Night and ſtole him away while the Watchmen ſlept, is too idle, and Contradictory to need a Confutation. What hopes could the poor ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Diſciples have to ſucceed in ſuch an attempt, and what end could they propoſe to ſerve if they ſhould ſucceed? What motive could prevail with them? Love to their Dead Maſter, and a deſign to get reputation to his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could never do it: For either they had ſome Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he ſhould riſe from the Dead, grounded upon the Scripture-Type, and Predictions, concerning the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, and the Applications which Jeſus had made of them to himſelf, or they had no ſuch Expectations: If they had no ſuch Expectations, if as the Evangeliſts tell us, <hi>they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53466:9"/>knew not the Scriptures, that he was to riſe from the Dead,</hi> if they were ſo far from expecting any ſuch thing, that when he was riſen, the Words of thoſe that reported it, <hi>ſeem'd to them as idle Tales,</hi> and they were not without great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſuaded to believe it, why then ſhould they attempt to ſteal him away, and make the World believe he was Riſen?</p>
            <p>But if they did expect his riſing again, obſerving what the Scriptures had foreſhewn of the Reſurrection of the Meſſias, and what he had promiſed for himſelf, as the great proof of his Authority and Religion, that <hi>in three Days he would raiſe again the Temple of his Body;</hi> Then, if after three Days he was not riſen, what ſhould move them to try with ſo much hazard to themſelves, to make Men believe he was riſen? Whereas, if he had fail'd them in this, they had all the reaſon in the World to look upon him as an Impoſtor, and themſelves as Cheated by him, who had avouched himſelf to be the Meſſias, and yet had not Anſwered the Characters given by the Prophets of the Meſſias, who had made himſelf the Antitype of <hi>Jonas,</hi> who lay three Days and Nights in the Whale's Belly, and declared that in conformity to the Type, he would lie three Days and Nights in the Belly of the Earth, and riſe again the third, and yet was ſo far from making this good, that after many three days, he ſtill lay Captivated under the Power of Death: When they were once convinced of this, it had been ſurely the greateſt madneſs in the World for them to expoſe themſelves to Dangers and Miſeries, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſo monſtrous a lie, either for the ſake of ſuch a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or of a Religion which ſuch an Impoſtor was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of.</p>
            <p>But I need not inſiſt upon this, for the Sepulchre was not only found empty, but he frequently appear'd and ſhew'd himſelf alive to ſeveral the very Day of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, that it might appear, that the Circumſtance of time, which he foretold, was fullfilled; And when his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53466:10"/>Diſciples upon his firſt appearance among them, (he ſhew'd himſelf three ſeveral times to them when they were Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together) were affrighted, ſuppoſing they had ſeen a Spirit, without any real Body, he calls for Meat and eats before them, he appeals to their Sences, bids them Handle him and Feel that he had a true Body conſiſting of Fleſh and Bone, and to convince them that 'twas the ſame Body that ſuffered, he ſhews them the Prints of the Nails in his Hands and Feet, and afterwards made <hi>Thomas,</hi> who it ſeems was reſolved to ſubmit to no leſs Conviction, to thruſt his hands into the Wound made by the Spear in his Side; and to ſupport the Teſtimony which theſe ſhould give of his Reſurrection, and to put it beyond all Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, he appear'd to more than Five hundred at once, and laſt of all to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who appeal'd to the greateſt part of that Five hundred as then living, for the proof of this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. So that this matter as it is laid in theſe Books, is ſo atteſted, that no one former thing in the whole World ever had that evidence of Fact.</p>
            <p>The ſum of what I have ſaid is this,</p>
            <p>The evidence of theſe Facts is ſo ſtrong, that whoever can disbelieve them, can never believe any thing that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd before his own time or out of his own ſight: The Facts are ſuch, that whoever believes they were done, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not disbelieve that Doctrine for the proof of which they were done, without believing that God who can no more deceive than be deceived, has miſled Men into the belief of a falſhood, in a matter, wherein it is of the greateſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to them not to be miſtaken, by the greateſt and moſt irreſiſtible External Evidence that can be had of the Truth of any thing: And conſequently thoſe to whom theſe Facts are thus made out, can have no good reaſon to deny or ſuſpend their Aſſents to that Religion, for the confirmation whereof theſe Works were wrought. What cloake they have for their Infidelity, what pretences they would cover it with, we ſhall ſee in the third and next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. And here</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53466:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis ſaid that the Chriſtian Religion has not been generally Reveal'd, and therefore cannot be neceſſary to future Happineſs; becauſe if it were, thoſe who could not know it, are out of a Poſſibility of a future State of Bleſſedneſs, which ſeems Inconſiſtent with God's Infinite goodneſs, who provides for all his Creatures, the means of attaining that Happineſs, whereof their Natures are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable. <hi>Orac. of Reaſ.</hi> p. 198, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The force of which objection depends upon a falſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; they take it for granted that we teach that thoſe who could not have any knowledge of the Chriſtian Religion are out of a capacity of being ſaved: Thus they would have it believ'd that we ſay, becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they have no ground for this Argument: But for our parts, we deny that our Church teaches any ſuch Doctrine.</p>
            <p>We do not determine Peremptorily of the Eternal State of the Heathens: we do not pretend <hi>to Judge thoſe that are without, to their own Maſter they ſtand or fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay indeed Infidelity is a damning Sin, but we mean not a Negative, but a Privative Infidelity, a want of Faith in a ſubject capable of it.</p>
            <p>We ſay there is no Salvation but through the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt; but ſay not whether or how far God may extend the benefit of thoſe Merits, to ſuch as live according to the beſt light they have, and whoſe unhappineſs, and not fault it is, that they want the light of Revelation.</p>
            <p>To be ſure they ſhall not be Judged by, or Condemned for not obeying, the Revealed Law, which being not made known could not be a Rule to them, but ſhall be tryed by the Law written in their Hearts: So St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly ſays, Rom. 2.14. <hi>The Gentiles having not the Law, are a Law to themſelves, which ſhew the Work of the Law written in their Hearts; their Conſcience alſo bearing witneſs, and their Thoughts the mean while accuſing, or elſe excuſing one another, in the Day when God ſhall Judge the ſecrets of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53466:11"/>
            <p>But if we are ſo Charitable to the Gentiles, why ſhould not we Judge as favourably of our Modern Deiſts?</p>
            <p>Their caſes are widely different. The former never heard of Chriſt or his Religion: Theſe have heard of, and yet oppoſe and revile both. And our Saviour has plainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in favour of the former, rather than theſe, in my Text, <hi>If I had not come and ſpoken unto them, they had not had Sin; but now they have no Cloke for their Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be objected againſt the Authority of the Scriptures, that there have ſeveral Books gone abroad in the World under the Names of the Sacred Writers, which are diſcover'd to be Forgerles.</p>
            <p>But ſurely 'tis no new diſcovery that there have been ſuch Books, or that they are Forgeries. The cheats have been long ſince detected, and the Books rejected by the Chriſtians. But what can be inferred from hence? Any thing to the prejudice of the Books which the Chriſtians own? Not in reaſon: For if another man ſhould write a Book in the name of a celebrated Author, or under the Title which his Works bear, and that Book ſhould afterwards appear to be Spurious, 'twould be very hard that this ſhould affect the credit of that Author's genuine Works.</p>
            <p>I think the conſequence turns the other way; and the Books falſly aſcribed to the Apoſtles, the counterfeit Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels and Epiſtles, prove that there were ſuch Men as the Apoſtles, that they were Authors, that there were true Goſpels and Epiſtles; for if there had never been ſuch Men, if they had not written, if there had been no true Goſpels and Epiſtles; we ſhould never have heard of Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Works under their Names, there would have been no ſuch counterfeit Goſpels and Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It may be ſaid farther to the prejudice of our Books, that ſome of thoſe which we do now receive, were for ſome time Queſtion'd by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But thoſe Queſtion'd Books contain'd nothing different from what was contain'd in thoſe that were never doubted of.</p>
            <p>And what can be the juſt inference from hence; but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53466:11"/>that Chriſtians were not eaſie credulous Perſons in theſe matters, but examined the Books well, and would be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly convinced of the truth of them before they would receive them?</p>
            <p>But to ſilence this Cavil, a Perſon whoſe Authority I ſuppoſe will paſs with our Deiſts, who was one of the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt Enemies to Chriſtianity, and Maſter of more Wit than his modern Followers, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperor I mean, owns thoſe Books to be the Writings of the Evangeliſts, and of the Apoſtles St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians read under their names. <hi>Cyril. Contr. Julian.</hi> p. 327.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It may be objected againſt the Miracles of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that the World has been much abuſed with accounts of falſe Miracles: Nay, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, they that pretend to be the only Society of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, have received many Miracles as ſtrange for quality as thoſe of Chriſt's, and with equal Faith; ſome of which they themſelves have ſince own'd to be falſe; and from hence it may be argued to the prejudice of Chriſt's Miracles, that if the Credulity of ſome later Ages has been thus impoſed upon, by cunning and deſigning Men, why may not the ſame or like Artifices have prevail'd in the firſt Chriſtian times?</p>
            <p>But this Objection will be eaſily anſwered by obſerving theſe differences between the Miracles of our Saviour, and the pretended ones of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Romiſh Miracles have either no Witneſſes, or ſuch as are made choice of for their known weakneſs or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality; none of them was ever atteſted by any Authors of known repute; whereas thoſe of Chriſt were wrought in the face of the World, and that a Knowing and Learned World, that reſiſted the Conviction to the utmoſt, but were forced by the Power of it to ſubmit; And of this we have ſuch aſſurance that no matter of Fact was ever ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to ſucceeding Ages.</p>
            <p>Again, the Romiſh Miracles were not done as ſigns to thoſe that believe not, but to thoſe that already believed; not before Sceptical Infidels or obſtinate Hereticks, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53466:12"/>
               <hi>Proſelytes</hi> already made and prepared for the ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion; that had put out their own Eyes, and renounced their own reaſon and ſenſes, and reſigned themſelves intirely to be governed by thoſe of their deſigning Leaders; and ſuch indeed might very eaſily be impoſed upon.</p>
            <p>But the caſe was very different with our Saviour's Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, where Men came with their Eyes as wide open as prejudice and intereſt could make them, to examine Facts which they would not have had to be true, and yet could not withſtand the Evidence, but were forced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the truth of them: and many of them that came with theſe prejudices were nevertheleſs by the Conviction of theſe Miracles brought over from a Religion they had ſuckt in with their Milk, that was ſupported by the ſuffrages of the Wiſe, and the Power and Countenance of the Great, to a New Religion, laught at by the one, and Perſecuted by the other.</p>
            <p>This was truly the caſe of the Chriſtian Religion at its firſt coming into the World: it appear'd with all the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages imaginable, was propoſed by the meaneſt and moſt contemptible Inſtruments, was oppoſed and ridiculed by the Learned of the Age, was threatned and moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely perſecuted by the Emperors and Potentates.</p>
            <p>And what Allurements did this Religion offer to draw Men through all theſe difficulties to it?</p>
            <p>Was there Honour or Reputation to be got by owning it? No alas! Our Saviour told his Diſciples, <hi>ye ſhall be hated of all Men for my Name ſake:</hi> They were call'd <hi>a Sect, that is every where ſpoke againſt:</hi> They <hi>were counted as the Dung and off-ſcouring of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did it propoſe Riches or Wealth? No, <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor, but wo unto you Rich; ſell what thou haſt and give alms:</hi> and <hi>how hardly ſhall a Rich man enter into the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did it offer eaſe and Pleaſures? No, <hi>In the World ye ſhall have Tribulation: ye ſhall be perſecuted and driven from this City to that, brought and accuſed before Kings and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors:</hi> And <hi>whoever kills you, will think he does God ſervice,</hi> Alas! this Religion lay'd no other Baits to allure Men to it,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53466:12"/>if it were not true, but Perſecution, Poverty, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Death.</p>
            <p>The conditions of Diſcipleſhip propoſed by our Lord are, <hi>If any Man will be my Diſciple, let him deny himſelf, take up his croſs, and follow me:</hi> He muſt <hi>hate</hi> his dear Relations, his dear Poſſeſſions, and his dearer Life too.</p>
            <p>Now certainly here was nothing in all this, that could Prepoſſeſs Men in favour of this Religion; or diſpoſe them to be eaſily wrought upon by the methods uſed for its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation, without a juſt enquiry into the truth and validity of them, that could make men deſpiſe all the difficulties that oppoſed them, and willingly run through all the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that threatned them, into it, without being fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed that God did really bear witneſs to it by <hi>ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and mighty works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, when the Chriſtian Religion firſt appear'd in the World, the Teachers of it uſed none of thoſe methods of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, Force or Flattery, which Impoſtors make uſe of, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigle or affright men into it; rather all things conſpired to diſcourage and affright them from it: The only Motive was this, that it was the way now propoſed by God, to attain Eternal Life; and the great Evidences and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of this were the Miracles wrought and appeal'd to by the Author and firſt Planters of it, which were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done in the face of the Sun, and ſight of Men who had liberty to examine them as nicely as they pleaſed: And it cannot be doubted by any one that conſiders their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of Education in a former Religion more agreeable to Fleſh and Blood, the Severities of this new one, and the Dangers from without which attended the embracers of it; but that, as theſe things made them very curious inquirers into the Truth of it; ſo that Truth was very apparent, when ſo many thouſands of all Ages, Sexes and Conditions, ran thro' Fire and Sword, &amp; Deaths of all kinds, into this New Religion.</p>
            <p>How ſpeedy and vaſt a Progreſs it made in the times of the Apoſtles, their Acts, and Epiſtles to the ſeveral Churche; founded by them, will inform us: and profane Authors,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53466:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Tacitus, Suetonius,</hi> and the younger <hi>Pliny</hi> tell us, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a Figure the Chriſtians made in the World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leſs than half a Century of the Apoſtles times: But by the end of the next Age they were ſpread all over the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology directed to the Roman Magiſtrates tells them. And though this mighty Progreſs of it Only made the Enemies thereof complain, that the City of <hi>Rome</hi> was environ'd on all ſides with the Enemies of the Gods, that the Chriſtians were ſpread all over the Empire, that the Provinces were full of them, and that there were Perſons among them of the greateſt Quality and Dignity; yet they ought, as that farther remarks, to have made this Inference from it, for undoubtedly it is a juſt one; that a Religion which, notwithſtanding all thoſe diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages above mention'd, drew all the Roman World after it, muſt needs have ſomething in it Excellent and Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> After all that is ſaid, the Deiſt ſtill thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very prudent and cautious; that he is on the ſafer ſide; and if <hi>he errs, he errs not like a Fool, but ſecundum verbum, after enquiry; and if he be ſincere in his principles, he can when dying appeal to God, Te deus bone, quaeſivi per omnia. Orac. of Reaſ. P.</hi> 92.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe it will be allow'd me, that they who have the greateſt Evidence that they are in the right, and run the leaſt riſque if they ſhould be miſtaken, act upon the moſt rational and prudent grounds, and are on the ſafer ſide. Let us then join iſſue here.</p>
            <p>The Evidence we have for our Religion is this. We ſay God himſelf has given Teſtimony to it, and we are ſure that his Teſtimony is true. That God has given Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to it, by Miracles wrought for the confirmation of it, we prove by the beſt Evidence a matter of this Nature is capable of; We produce a whole Cloud of Witneſſes, who relate theſe Facts upon their knowledge, who could have no intereſt to ſerve by prevaricating, who ventur'd their All upon the truth of them, who ſeal'd their Teſtimony with their Bloud. And this is convey'd down to us in ſuch a manner, that if it be falſe, it is not poſſible for us to be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53466:13"/>ſure that any thing, which we did not ſee is true; &amp; alſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with variety of Collateral Proofs, Records and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Enemies as well as Friends of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that to disbelieve them is not Scepticiſm but Madneſs.</p>
            <p>Now what proof does or can the Deiſt urge againſt us? Why, he muſt proteſt againſt a matter of Fact, he muſt ſuppoſe all our Scriptures, and all the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers writings wherein they are quoted, to be Forgeries, and thoſe of Jews and Heathens who have wrote againſt them to be ſo too: Or elſe that all theſe have been corrupted by the unanimous conſent of all Chriſtians among whom they were diſperſed over the World; who all agreed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver in their Books, not any denying ſo to do, or owning or complaining of it; and received them again ſo interpolated; and yet ſtill ventured their Salvation upon the truth of them: Or he muſt ſuppoſe that a great number of honeſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſigning Men would not only lye for lying ſake, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than not impoſe it upon the World, would dye Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs to a lye, and that multitudes of Perſons of all Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſwallow'd theſe lyes, either without Examination, tho' they were matters of the higheſt Importance to them, or elſe after that upon Examination they had found them to be ſo: And yet ſo obſtinately believed them, that they ſtaked Body and Soul, quitted their Eſtates, Liberties, Lives, all their enjoyments in this World, and ventur'd upon them all their hopes in the next: So that I think the matter is pretty clear on the Chriſtians ſide as to point of Evidence.</p>
            <p>As to Danger, if the Chriſtian runs any hazard, it muſt be, becauſe his Religion is deficient in ſomething neceſſary to be believed or practiſed in order to Salvation, or it impoſes ſome things upon his belief or practice inconſiſtent with it.</p>
            <p>As to the former I do aſſert that there are no Doctrines in Natural Religion relating to Faith or Practice, to God, our Neighbour, or our ſelves, to the duties we owe to each, or the obligations we lie under to diſcharge thoſe duties, but what are more clearly explain'd, the duties enjoin'd in a more extenſive meaning, and enforced by more Powerful ſanctions in the Chriſtian, than in the Natural Religion.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53466:14"/>
            <p>As to the other, the Articles of Faith and poſitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions peculiar to Chriſtianity, I do affirm, that we are not obliged to believe any thing, that is unworthy of God, repugnant to any principle of right Reaſon, or that can have any ill influence upon our lives: nor are we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do any thing that tends to the diſhonour of God, to the withdrawing of our ſervice from him, or making us ſlack in the performance of our duty to him: But contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the Doctrines and Inſtitutions of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are all, as I could ſhew, if I had time, calculated for the uniting of our Souls to God, the exciting of our fear and reverence, the inflaming of our Love, the ſtricter tying us to, and quick'ning us in our obedience to him. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doctrines and Practiſes not only ſo innocent, but of ſo good a tendency, eſpecially when we have ſuch Grounds to believe them propoſed and commanded by God, as a prudent and conſidering Man will judge Rational, will, although we could be ſuppoſed to be out in this belief, yet be lookt upon as at leaſt very pardonable errors by our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God.</p>
            <p>But if the Deiſt be miſtaken, and that Religion which he rejects, and is the object of his laughter and ſcorn, ſhould prove True at laſt, what a miſerable condition muſt he be in?</p>
            <p>I grant a Religion's condemning all thoſe that do not comply with it, is no ſure Argument of the truth of it: but the Truth of it being ſuppoſed, it is a very good proof of the Danger they are in that reject it.</p>
            <p>Now the Propoſals of the Goſpel are ſet forth as the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt effects and ſtruggle of the Divine Compaſſion, the laſt tenders of Mercy to Mankind: We are there told, that for thoſe, <hi>who neglect that great Salvation there is no eſcape, nothing remains more but a fearful expectation of fiery indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> The tenor of it is, <hi>he that believes ſhall be ſaved, but he that believes not ſhall be damn'd:</hi> nay it declares that the Judgment of thoſe who refuſe it, after it has been propoſed to them, ſhall be heavier than if there had never been any ſuch offer made to them.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53466:14"/>
            <p>And what has the Infidel to Plead, by which he can hope to mitigate his Crime or his Puniſhment? Why, only that he had not other or more Evidence for the truth of the Goſpel's Revelations than the matter would bear: that God did not uſe ſuch irreſiſtible means for his Conviction, as are not conſiſtent with the Liberty of a free Agent, and would have made his Faith to have been no Virtue. And what then can he expect, but that ſince he would not be convinced by the great Moral Evidence that was tender'd to him of the truth of the Doctrines of the Goſpel, he ſhould feel a ſenſible and experimental conviction, of the truth and reality of the Threats of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It now only remains that I ſhut up all with one Word of Practical application: If he that does not believe the Goſpel has no cloke for his Infidelity, what cloke can we, that do believe it, but not obey it, have for our diſobedience? <hi>What does it profit if a Man ſay he has Faith, and has not Works, will Faith ſave him?</hi> a dead Faith without any Vital acts flowing from it? No, our Maſter has told us, 'tis to no purpoſe to <hi>call him Lord, Lord,</hi> to give up our names to him and profeſs our ſelves his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, unleſs <hi>we do the things which he commands us.</hi> And this command we have very particularly in charge from him, <hi>that he that loves God loves his Brother alſo.</hi> Vain is that <hi>Faith that doth not work by love,</hi> and falſe that pretended love to God, that is not attended with a love to our Brother.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian inſtitution is ſingular in the injunction of Charity. No other inſtitution ever underſtood it in ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive a meaning, both as to the objects and exerciſe of it; ever commanded it ſo ſtrictly, perſuaded ſo Pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, or propoſed ſuch glorious rewards to it.</p>
            <p>The objects of Chriſtian Charity are as large as all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, not only Relations and Friends but Strangers and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53466:15"/>
            <p>The Exerciſe of it is to reach as far as our Brethrens wants and our own Abilities will go, even to the <hi>laying down of our</hi> lives upon ſome Occaſions for them.</p>
            <p>The Commands that enjoin it are moſt frequent and emphatical in this Chapter; verſe 12. <hi>This is my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſays our Lord, <hi>that ye love one another,</hi> and v. 17. <hi>Theſe things I command you that ye love one another:</hi> and in 13 cap. v. 34. <hi>A new commandment give I unto you;</hi> and that ſuch as ſhall be the diſtinguiſhing Badge of your Profeſſion, <hi>by which all Men ſhall know that you are my Diſciples; that you have love one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſiderations by which this is preſſed upon us are moſt moving: <hi>viz.</hi> the Infinite love of Chriſt to us, who will look upon the kindneſs we ſhew to our poor Brethren as done to himſelf; the near Relation we ſtand in to one another, not only as being <hi>made of one Fleſh,</hi> but as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Baptized into one Body, and ſo more ſtrictly ally'd as being members of the ſame myſtical Body, which ought to have the ſame Sympathy and Fellow feeling with one another as the members of the Body Natural have; The excellency of this Grace, in that 'tis preferable <hi>to Faith and Hope, the very bond of perfectneſs, the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> and <hi>that it ſhall cover a multitude of Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Eternal Glories of Heaven are promiſed to the due performance of it, St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 25. where our Saviour and Judge deſcribes the procedure of the laſt Judgment, as if the only thing he ſhould then come to enquire into were our Obedience or Diſobedience to this Royal Law.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, Charity is ſo Eſſential to Chriſtianity, that an irrational Man is not a greater Contradiction than an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The firſt Chriſtians were ſo ſenſible of this, that they would ſcarce call <hi>ought of the things they poſſeſs'd their own:</hi> They thought their Poor Brethren had as good a Title to what they could ſpare, as they themſelves had to the reſt of their Eſtates; and they ſo ordered matters, that thoſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53466:15"/>who had a great deal, and thoſe who had nothing, were like the <hi>Iſraelites that gathered much or little Manna, the former had nothing over, and the latter had no lack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed there never was any Society of Chriſtians that did not think they ought to diſtinguiſh themſelves from Perſons of any other Denomination by <hi>abounding in this Grace.</hi> Even the worſt Society, that of <hi>Rome,</hi> is not deficient in the exerciſe of it towards the Bodies of thoſe of their own Communion, tho' 'tis to be fear'd the merit of that Charity will be over-ballanced by their want of it towards both the Bodies and Souls of thoſe that differ from them.</p>
            <p>But I need not <hi>take occaſion by the forwardneſs</hi> of Papiſts, <hi>to prove the ſincerity of your Love;</hi> ſince we have in this City ſo many Noble inſtances of Publick Charities, ſince the Reformation, to provoke your Emulation: Some of which when I reflect upon, methinks I ſee ſome faint reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, ſuch as Poor imperfect Creatures can make, of the Lord himſelf <hi>going about doing good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See him expreſſing his tenderneſs to little Children, in that Pious care that is taken of Poor Orphans in the Hoſpital that bears his Name.</p>
            <p>See him reſtoring uſe of Limbs to the Lame, ſight to the Blind, healing the maim'd, and curing all manner of Diſeaſes, in that variety of Charitable Cures, that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in the Hoſpitals of St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See him making a Whip of ſmall Cords, and ſcourging the tranſgreſſors, in thoſe Juſt Corrections that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed upon the vicious in <hi>Bridewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See him reſtoring the Lunaticks to their right Minds, in thoſe excellent methods that are uſed with Poor diſtracted Wretches in <hi>Bethlem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall poſſeſs you with a Juſter notion of theſe Great Charities by reading to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true report,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You ſee here at once, both noble examples of Charity to excite your imitation, and very worthy and preſſing oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions for the exerciſe of it.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53466:16"/>
            <p>Will you Pardon me if I mention one other kind of Charity, the bare naming of which, will I think, be ſufficient to recommend it to the encouragement of all well-diſpoſed Perſons; I mean building Work-Houſes, and providing a ſtock to ſet the Poor to Work?</p>
            <p>I mention this with the more aſſurance becauſe I find it is a way you are going into, and have already made ſome progreſs in it: And were it carryed on with unanimity and reſolution to bring it to perfection, and managed (as I am confident it will be in this City) with Care and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and a ſingle Eye to the publick good, 'twould certainly turn to a very excellent account.</p>
            <p>'Twould not only be a great Charity to the Poor, to their Souls as well as Bodies, to keep them from Begging and Thieving, and put them in an honeſt way of getting their living; but to employ thoſe that are now the burdens and peſts of the Kingdom in Working up our Manufactures, would be a Publick Benefaction.</p>
            <p>And now my Brethren, ſince Charity is ſo Special and Eminent a Duty of that Religion which our Lord taught and confirm'd to us; ſince all his true Followers have ever lookt upon and practiſed it as the diſtinguiſhing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of their Profeſſion; let us, having ſuch glorious Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns before our Eyes to encourage us, and ſuch and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Opportunities now put into our Hands of exerciſing this Grace, make uſe of theſe Opportunities, and therein follow thoſe excellent Patterns. Without this, I am ſure, how firmly ſoever we may believe our Religion our ſelves, and however ſtrongly we may argue for it with others, 'tis not poſſible we ſhould offer any thing ſucceſsfully to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of our Conſciences or Conviction of other Mens: As to our ſelves if we do believe our Religion, we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what it tells us; that all the greateſt Qualifications and Performances without this ſignify nothing, that even our Faith is dead and our Hope preſumption: And as to others, 'tis in vain to think to perſuade them to embrace a Religion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53466:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>by any thing we can ſay, when they muſt judge by which what we do, that we our ſelves deſpiſe and believe it not worth obſerving.</p>
            <p>If we would prevail with others to believe the Truth of our Religion, we muſt firſt convince them that we believe it our ſelves. But if we can live in the open neglect of, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed defiance to its Precepts, eſpecially ſuch an Eminent one as this, let us talk as long as we will for it, men can never believe we are in earneſt.</p>
            <p>If any one Duty be more frequently and forcibly enjoin'd in our Religion than another, 'tis this of Charity; which when it proceeds from a right principle, and is directed to a right end, is the Glory as well as Duty of a Chriſtian: but if a man, however otherwiſe endow'd, cannot <hi>ſhew out of a good Coniverſation his Works with meekneſs of Wiſdom, that Wiſdom, that is full of Mercy and good Fruits,</hi> all his Boaſting and <hi>Glorying</hi> upon other accounts, <hi>is but a lying againſt the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We live in an Age wherein our Religion is not only under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by thoſe that are Working in the Dark, but more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly aſſaulted by open and avowed Enemies. The <hi>Weapons</hi> wherewith we are to encounter them are <hi>not Carnal.</hi> That which is more immediately our Poſt, who are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, is to Write, Preach, and Argue for holy Religion: that which is Yours in common with us, is to Live for it. And did we all but live with that ſtrictneſs of Piety, and Purity, which it enjoins, and we profeſs; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>whatever things are honeſt, chaſt, lovely, and of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; above all putting on Charity, putting on as the elect of God, bowels of mercies and kindneſs;</hi> we might yet hope to ſee it flouriſh in ſpite of all the Power and Malice of its Enemies.</p>
            <p>That which very much contributed to the ſpeedy and wide ſpreading of the Chriſtian Religion at firſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the mighty oppoſition that was made to it, was the Exemplary behaviour of the Profeſſors of it, and in particular that ſhining Charity which they were ſo eminent for.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53466:17"/>
            <p>And this will ever be a moſt certain method to ſecure and propagate our Religion, it will procure the Bleſſing and Protection of God, it will be a means of convincing men of the reality of our Faith in the rewards of another Life, when they ſee us for the ſake of them, ſo willingly part with the good things of this. It muſt have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ry Natural tendency to diſpoſe thoſe that partake of our C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive impreſſions from our Exhortations; and it muſt give all that hear of it an amiable Idea of our Religion, when they find that the employment of a Chriſtian is like that of our great Maſter. Our good Works ſo ſhining forth, with a bright and pure Flame, muſt induce not only thoſe that feel the warmth of it, but thoſe alſo, that ſee the Light, to join with us in Glorifying our Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>SERMONS <hi>by the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Oxford, <hi>and Printed for</hi> Tho. Bennet.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at the Cathedral Church of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> upon a Faſt-Day. Publiſh'd at the requeſt of the Mayor and Aldermen of that City.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd before the Late Queen at <hi>Whitehall.</hi> Publiſh'd by Her Majeſty's Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs and Miſchief of Atheiſm.</hi> A Sermon Preach'd before the Late Queen at <hi>Whitehall.</hi> Publiſh'd by her Majeſty's Special Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fooliſh Abuſe and wiſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Riches.</hi> A Sermon Preach'd at the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Bromeſgrove,</hi> in <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> Upon Occaſion of a Charity given to that Place, by Sir <hi>Tho. Cookes</hi> of <hi>Bentley,</hi> Knight and Barr.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at the Cathedral Church of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> upon a Thankſgiving-Day. Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of the Mayor and Aldermen of that City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spirit of Popery tryed whether it be of God.</hi> A Sermon Preach'd before the King at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> upon the 5th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 1699. Publiſh'd by His Majeſty's Special Command.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53466:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
